Doctor Who (1963) 04x09  The Evil of the Daleks (Episode 4)
《神秘博士》老版第四季第九集 《Daleks 的邪恶》 (第四部分)
【翻译】巴蛮子sz
【时间轴】巴蛮子sz
【校对】巴蛮子sz
基于 opentitles.org 英文字幕翻译
Hello? Who are you?
你好？你是谁？
(Sincro: wyxchari)
(Kemel runs towards Jamie gripping him in a bear hug.)
（Kemel 朝 Jamie 跑过来，一个熊抱扑住了他）
(He manages to break free.)
Jamie 用力挣脱了
(Kemel knocks Jamie to the floor.)
Kemel 又把 Jamie 撞到在地上
(Lashing out with his leg, Jamie sends Kemel crashing into  a suit of armour.)
Jamie 伸出腿，把 Kemel 绊倒，Kemel 摔倒在一副盔甲中
(Jamie runs through an open door and slams it shut.)
Jaime 跑过一道门，砰地一下关上
(Kemel recovers and sets off after Jamie.)
Kemel 爬起身来，又来追 Jaime
(Jame takes a sword from the wall.)
Jamie 从墙上抄起一把剑
(Jamie hears Kemel approaching.)
他听见 Kemel 走近了
(Kemel runs towards Jamie, He jumps out of the way.)
Kemel 朝 Jamie 跑过来，Jamie 一跳躲开了
(Kemel goes flying out of a window, catching the guttering to save himself.)
Kemel 从窗户飞了出去，急伸手抓住了屋檐
(Jamie climbs onto the roof.)
Jaime 爬到了屋顶上
(Kemel is unable to pull himself up.)
Kemel 没法把自己的身子拉上来
(Jamie helps Kemel to climb back onto the roof.)
Jaime 拉 Kemel，帮他爬回了屋顶
(A Dalek goes by, unnoticed, on the floor below.)
他们没注意到，一个 Dalek 从下面走过
(The Dalek places the handkerchief in an empty room.)
这个 Dalek 把手绢放入了一个空房间
(Kemel lowers Jamie to the first floor.)
Kemel 吊着 Jamie，把他放到了地板上
(Jamie spots the handkerchief.)
Jamie 看到了手绢
(Kemel pulls Jamie clear as a blade comes crashing down.)
(Jamie and Kemel exchange glances, then Kemel helps the dazed Jamie from the room.)
(They go up a flight of stairs.)
DOCTOR: It took courage to fight Maxtible's Turkish wrestler.
跟 Maxtible 的土耳其斗士搏斗, 是很需要勇气的
DALEK: The Daleks are afraid of nothing and no one.
Daleks 不怕任何东西, 也不怕任何人
DOCTOR: But Jamie saved the Turk's life.
但 Jamie 又救了那个土耳其人的命
DALEK: Human weakness.
人类的弱点
DOCTOR: If he hadn't, he would have died in that room of yours.
If you want the Human Factor, a part of it must include mercy.
如果他没有救, 他就会死在你们的房间里了。如果你想要人类特质, “仁慈”肯定是其中一项
WATERFIELD: What... what is he doing here?
他。。。他在这里做什么？
MAXTIBLE: A common thief, come to see what he could steal.
No mystery here.
一个普通小贼, 进来看看有什么可偷的, 估计就是这样
DALEK: The intruder was destroyed.
闯入者已经被毁灭
WATERFIELD: Well, what... what are we to do? Where is the Doctor?
He must be told.
那。。。我们该怎么办？博士哪儿去了？肯定得告诉他啊
DALEK: No.
不用
WATERFIELD: Why not?
为什么不用？
DALEK: Obey me!
服从我!
MAXTIBLE: Waterfield, I... I beg of you, do not antagonize the, um...
Waterfield, 我求你了, 不要激怒这些。。。唔
MAXTIBLE: ...our friends.
。。。朋友
WATERFIELD: Oh, why do you consistently avoid reality, Maxtible?
Another man has died. Can't you grasp that fact?
噢, 你为什么一直都要逃避现实呢, Maxtible？又一个人死了, 你还没看明白吗？
DALEK: You will hide the remains of the dead human intruder.
你要把这位闯入者的尸体藏起来
WATERFIELD: No!
不!
DELKS: That is an order!
这是一项命令！
MAXTIBLE: We must do as they say, Waterfield. We... we cannot anger them.
我们必须按他们说的做, Waterfield. 我们。。。我们不能激怒他们
MAXTIBLE: Here. Wrap the body in this.
这里, 把尸体卷到这里面来
WATERFIELD: No.
不
(Maxtible takes a dust sheet from beneath the bench.)
（Maxtible 从工作台下拿出一个防尘板）
MAXTIBLE: We must! Have you lost your mind?
我们得干！你疯了吗？
MAXTIBLE: Don't you want to see your daughter again?
不想再见到你女儿了？
WATERFIELD: Th... there's no end to this. The hands of the Devil.
这。。。这有没有个尽头, 魔鬼的手
DALEK: Dispose of the body. Obey!
处理掉尸体。服从！
(The Dalek enters the cabinet.)
MAXTIBLE：Waterfield, what is the matter with you?
We are not to blame for everything that has happened.
Waterfield, 你到底是怎么了？发生了这一切, 并不是我们的错啊
MAXTIBLE: No English judge or jury would find it in their hearts
to convict us of one solitary thing.
这里的任何一件事, 没有那个英国法官或者陪审团在他们的心里会认为该定我们的罪
WATERFIELD: It will never come to that.
不会到那一步的
MAXTIBLE: And what may that remark mean?
这句话是什么意思？
WATERFIELD: I have one purpose only: to see my daughter
out of the hands of those foul monsters.
我就一个目的：看到我的女儿逃出这些怪物的魔爪
WATERFIELD: When that is achieved, I shall confess my part
in all that has happened.
一旦这个目的达到了, 我会坦白我在所有这一切中所扮演的角色
(Waterfield drags the body away.)
(Maxtible goes to a drawer, takes out a pistol and puts it into his coat.)
WATERFIELD: Y... You must help me.
你。。。你必须帮我
MAXTIBLE: I am at your heels, my dear sir.
我马上就来, 我亲爱的朋友
JAMIE: That's better, thank you.
Aye, you're an odd one. I'll say that.
好多了, 谢谢你。啊, 你是个奇怪的家伙, 我得说。
JAMIE: Aye, well, I... I suppose we're both a a bit touched, eh?
啊, 我猜咱们俩都有点感动了, 对不？
JAMIE: Knocking each other about the place and saving one another's lives.
在这里打得死去活来, 然后又相互救了对方的命
JAMIE: You don't say much, do you?
你很少说话, 是吧
JAMIE: Oh, I see. You can't talk?
哦, 我明白了, 你不能说话？
JAMIE: Aye. Well, you're a sight better than a number of people I know who can.
啊, 这样啊, 你比我认识的很多会说话的人还好
JAMIE: I wonder what your name is?
你叫什么名字？
(Kemmel writes his name in the dust.)
JAMIE: Kemel? Well, I'm Jamie.
Kemel? 我叫 Jamie
(Kemel bows.)
JAMIE: He... hey, what is that?! Now come on now.
None of that. We're to be friends. Do you hear? Friends.
嘿。。嘿, 这什么意思？起来吧, 不要这样, 我们要做的是朋友, 你明白吗？朋友
(Kemel pulls a flower, wrapped in a paper from his belt.)
（Kemel 从他的腰带上拿出一朵花, 外面抱着一层纸）
JAMIE: Aye. "V.W." I know, Victoria Waterfield.
啊, "V.W." 我知道, 代表 Victoria Waterfield
(Kemel points to the handkerchief. Then unwraps the flower.)
JAMIE: Oh, Miss Waterfield gave you the flower? You like her?
哦, Waterfield 小姐给了你这朵花？你喜欢她？
JAMIE: Of course. Then what are we fighting for?
当然是了。那我们还打什么呀？
JAMIE: Do you not know what I'm doing here, Kemel?
Victoria Waterfield is being held a prisoner here somewhere.
你知道我到这里来干什么的吧, Kemel? Victoria 被囚禁在这里的某个地方
(Kemel looks at Jamie, then up the the dark passage.)
(He points to himeself, then Jamie and finally to the passage.)
JAMIE: Together? Aye, we'll go together. There's no one
I'd rather have with me.
一起？好, 我们一起去。现在我也不愿意其他人跟我在一起
(The Doctor is busy making calculations.)
(They carry the body into the stables.)
WATERFIELD: What was that? Did you hear it?
那是什么？你听到了a吗？
MAXTIBLE: Control your nerves.
别紧张
WATERFIELD: But there was a noise.
刚才的确有声音
MAXTIBLE: Waterfield, go back to the house.
Waterfield, 回到房子里去
WATERFIELD: Hmm? Oh, we have a task to perform.
唔, 我们还有任务得干呢
MAXTIBLE: Waterfield, I am sick to death of you.
Waterfield, 我真是被你恶心死了
WATERFIELD: What?
怎么了？
MAXTIBLE: I take you into my house, you and your daughter - provide for you.
我把你们 - 你和你女儿 - 带到我的房子来, 还供你们吃住
WATERFIELD: Yes, I know everything that you've done.
是的, 我知道你做的这一切
MAXTIBLE: Small thanks do I get for it! I did not bring these terrible
creatures here deliberately, you know that. Am I to blame for everything?
但我得到了多少感谢？这些可怕的生物也不是我特意带来的, 你知道的, 这一切该怪我吗？
WATERFIELD: No, no.
不, 不应该
MAXTIBLE: No, it is your daughter they have kidnapped. One moment,
you beg me to do everything I can to rescue her; next moment, you blame me.
他们绑架的是你的女儿。这一会儿, 你求我做这做那以救她回来, 过一会儿, 你又怪我
WATERFIELD: Yes. I... I don't mean it like that.
It's the price. First Kennedy, now this fellow.
是的。。。我并不是那个意思。这都是代价。先是 Kennedy, 现在又是这家伙
WATERFIELD: How many people must die so that my daughter can live?
要死多少人才能救回我女儿?
MAXTIBLE: We are not the murderers!
我们又不是凶手！
WATERFIELD: No, just the silent partners. But we're equally to blame
because we stand by and do nothing.
不是，只是沉默的帮凶。但我们同样是有罪的，因为我们只是站在一边什么也不做
MAXTIBLE: Go back to the house, Waterfield. I... I understand
you are under a stress. You... you try and get some sleep.
回你的房间去吧，Waterfield。我。。我明白你现在压力比较大。你。。你试试睡一觉吧
WATERFIELD: Sleep? I've not had one good night's rest since this started.
睡觉？我一晚也没有睡好过，自打这事开始
MAXTIBLE: There. You go back to your room.
Near the end now. You've done enough.
去吧，回到你的房间去。快结束了。你已经做得够多了。
(Waterfield turns to leave. Maxtible takes out his gun.)
MAXTIBLE: What... what are you doing?
你。。你在干什么？
TERRALL: Waterfield does not die yet!
Waterfield 现在还不能死
MAXTIBLE: He says he will confess everything!
他说他会全部供出一切的
(Terrall takes the gun.)
TERRALL: Go back to the laboratory. I will dispose of the body.
You will obey. You will obey!
回到实验室去。我会处理掉尸体的。你必须服从，你必须服从
(Jamie and Kemel watch a Dalek go by.)
JAMIE: Wait. Never mind about those, Kemel,
unless they catch sight of us.
等等, 别管那些家伙, Kemel, 除非他们看到我们了。
We seem to be going in the right direction.
看来我们走对方向了
(The Doctor continues to program the computer panel.)
(Jamie knocks a button with his hand.)
JAMIE: Down!
趴下
(A heavy metal ball swings out from the light.)
DALEK: We do not trust you. What thoughts are you using now?
我们不相信你。你现在在想什么？
DOCTOR: Human beings have five senses: sight, hearing, taste, smell and touch.
人类有五种感觉：视觉、听觉、味觉、嗅觉和触觉。
DOCTOR: But there is instinct too. And Jamie used instinct to avoid your trap.
但还有一种叫做自觉。Jamie 就是用自觉避开了你们的陷阱
(Jamie and Kemel watch from the shadows.)
(A light shines on the minstrels’ gallery door and the door opens.)
DALEK: Name?
名字?
VICTORIA: Victoria.
维多利亚!
DALEK: Louder.
大声点
VICTORIA: Victoria! Victoria Waterfield! You know my name!
维多利亚! 维多利亚-瓦特菲尔德! 你们知道我的名字!
DALEK: Silence. Inspection is over. Return to your room.
收声。检视结束了。回到你的房间去
(The door closes and the lights goes out.)
JAMIE: She's very beautiful, Kemel.
她很漂亮，Kemel
(Kemel takes a mace from the wall.)
JAMIE: What are you going to do with that?
你打算拿着那个干什么用？
(Kemel points it towards the Dalek.)
JAMIE: You'll attack the Daleks - draw them off down the corridor,
你要攻击那些 Daleks, 把他们吸引到走廊里？
(Kemel nods, then points to the stairs.)
JAMIE: while I go up there and rescue her somehow?
好让我上那儿去, 把她救出来？
JAMIE: It's too dangerous, Kemel. Besides, needs two of us up there. But how?
这太危险了, Kemel。另外, 需要两个人都进去才行。怎么办？
DALEK: What is the significance of this thought pattern?
这个思维模式有什么用？
DOCTOR: Suicidal attacks to gain an objective are stupid
为了赢得一个目标而进行自杀性袭击, 是愚蠢的
DOCTOR: Self-preservation is a strong human factor.
自我保护是一种很强的人类特质
DOCTOR: Jamie and his new friend are determined to succeed.
Jamie 和他的新朋友注定了会成功
DOCTOR: But finding the girl is only part. Getting her away is another.
但找到这个女孩儿是一回事, 能把她救走又是另外一回事
TERRALL: You'll come in here, Mollie, and explain yourself.
你给我进来, Mollie, 解释清楚
MOLLIE: Oh... Oh, sir... Please, sir... You're hurting me!
噢。。噢, 先生。。求你了, 先生。。你弄疼我了
TERRALL: Now, what is this hysterical nonsense?
说说, 到底是怎么一回事？
MOLLIE: But sir, I heard Miss Victoria's voice!
但是, 先生, 我听到 Victoria 小姐的声音了
TERRALL: Did she say how the weather was in Paris? That's where she is, Mollie.
那她说了巴黎的天气如何了吗？那是她现在呆的地方, Mollie
MOLLIE: Well, I know that sir, but I heard her speaking.
是的, 我知道, 先生。但我的确听到她说话了
TERRALL: Where?
在哪儿？
MOLLIE: I was walking past the big fireplace in the hall sir,
and her voice sort of... floated out of it.
我从大厅的大壁炉前经过的时候, 先生, 她的声音就。。。飘了过来
TERRALL: Will you explain how you could possibly hear
Miss Waterfield's voice when she's in Paris?!
那你解释一下既然 Waterfield 在巴黎, 你怎么能听到她的声音？
MOLLIE: I know it can't be, sir, but I heard her, as plain as anything.
我知道这不可能, 先生, 但我听到她了, 的确是她的
TERRALL: What were you doing in the hall?
那你那会儿在大厅里面干什么？
MOLLIE: Oh, well. I wasn't doing anything wrong, sir.
哦, 这个, 我并没有干什么坏事, 先生
TERRALL: What were you doing in this part of the house at this hour?!
你到底在这间房子里面做什么, 都这个时间了？
MOLLIE: Oh, I don't know.
噢, 我不知道
TERRALL: You do know, and you'll tell me!
你知道, 你得告诉我！
RUTH: Arthur!
TERRALL: I found this child creeping about the corridors.
我发现这个小丫头在走廊里鬼鬼祟祟的
MOLLIE: I haven't done anything.
我什么也没干
TERRALL: Be quiet!
收声！
MOLLIE: Yes sir.
是, 先生
TERRALL: She's miles from her room - should have been in bed an hour since!
她离她房间房间这么远 - 一个小时前就该上床睡觉了！
RUTH: Did you have extra work this morning?
你早上是不是还有活儿要做？
MOLLIE: Yes, Miss Ruth. I do.
是的, Ruth 小姐, 还有
TERRALL: You're a liar!
你在撒谎！
MOLLIE: Well, I haven't done anything, Miss. I haven't took nothing.
真的, 我什么也没做, 小姐。我什么也没拿
RUTH: Arthur, the poor child's frightened out of her skin after this.
Arthur, 这可怜的小丫头都吓得不行了
TERRALL: She's nothing but play acting. She's a mean, sniveling little minx.
她这都是在假扮无辜呢, 她是个带着假面的恶毒小妖精
MOLLIE: But I haven't done anything. I haven't.
但我什么也没有做过, 没有
TERRALL: Go to the sitting room and wait there.
Mr. Maxtible will decide what to do with you.
到客厅去等着, Maxtible 先生会决定对你如何处置
MOLLIE: But sir, I...
但是先生, 我。。。
TERRALL: Do as you are told!
照我说的做！
RUTH: Come on, it's all right. Everything will be all right.
来吧, 没事的, 一切都会弄明白的
RUTH: Arthur, tell me what's wrong.
Authur, 告诉我哪里不对劲？
TERRALL: Wrong? Why should something be wrong?
不对劲？为什么得有什么事不对劲？
RUTH: Has my father influenced you in some way?
我父亲跟你说了什么吗？
TERRALL: No, not your father.
不, 不是你父亲
RUTH: Come away with me please! I somehow feel if we delay, it will be too late.
请跟我来吧。不知怎么的, 我感觉如果我们再拖的话, 就太迟了
TERRALL: I can't go. Not yet.
我不能去, 还不到时候
MAXTIBLE: I have done everything you have asked me to.
你们让我做的所有事情, 我都做了
MAXTIBLE: You wanted an agency here on Earth to plan and prepare things for you. I have been that agency.
你们想要在地球上有一个代理机构，帮你们做些谋划和准备, 我就成了这个代理
MAXTIBLE: Will you please tell those who give you orders that
I am getting tired of waiting.
你能不能转告那些下命令的, 说我已经厌倦了等待了
DALEK: Do you threaten the Daleks?
你是在威胁 Daleks 吗?
MAXTIBLE: Oh, surely threatening is not necessary. We have a...
a partnership - an understanding.
噢, 当然了并不是威胁。我们。。。是有伙伴关系, 有共识的
DALEK: You have obeyed us.
你一直很听话
MAXTIBLE: You have a strange way of putting things.
你们的表达方式很奇怪
MAXTIBLE: I prefer to say that you have asked for certain services.
我倒愿意用这样的说法：你们请求我们提供某些服务
MAXTIBLE: I have, uh... provided those services punctually and efficiently.
我也一直很高效很准确地提供了这些服务
MAXTIBLE: Now you really must look to your side of the bargain.
但你们现在真的必须看一下你们这边了
MAXTIBLE: It is not beyond me to ruin the entire enterprise.
我还真是不能理解, 你们会毁了这笔交易
MAXTIBLE: Oh, oh, oh, ho!
噢, 噢, 噢, 噢！
DALEK: Do not threaten! Obey!
不要威胁我们! 要服从！
MAXTIBLE: Yes, very well! I understand!
好, 好的！我懂了！
DALEK: Obey the Daleks.
服从 Daleks
MAXTIBLE: No. Please... Please wait!
不, 求你了, 等等！
MAXTIBLE: The secret... the secret. You promised to give it to me!
That is why I have done all this!
秘密, 那个秘密。你们承诺了给我的！所以我才做这一切的啊！
DALEK: The Daleks know many secrets. You will learn the most important.
Daleks 知道很多秘密, 你将会得到最重要的
(The Dalek returns to the cabinet.)
MAXTIBLE: I must not be frightened of them.
我不能被他们吓倒
MAXTIBLE: It's just their way. Th... They're different people - alien.
这是他们的方式。。他们跟我们不同, 是外星人
MAXTIBLE: But they will tell me! Of course they will!
但他们会告诉我的, 当然会！
RUTH: Father!
父亲
MAXTIBLE: Ruth, I told you not to come in here - under any circumstances.
Ruth, 我告诉过你不要到这里来, 不管任何情况下
RUTH: Father, I simply had to.
I heard you speaking to someone and there's no one here.
父亲, 我只是不得不来。我听到你在跟谁说话, 但这里没有人
And Arthur is involved in some way.
而且 Arthur 不知怎么也卷进来了
MAXTIBLE: Oh, Arthur. Yes.
哦, Arthur, 是的
RUTH: Why has he become so changed?
And Victoria Waterfield - where is she?
为什么他变化这么大？ 还有 Victoria Waterfield, 她在哪儿？
MAXTIBLE: My child, these are questions that I cannot answer.
我的孩子, 这些问题我都回答不了
MAXTIBLE: But, my dear, I will tell you one thing - one thing only,
不过, 亲爱的, 我可以告诉你一件事 - 就这一件
MAXTIBLE: and then perhaps you may understand why there are secrets to be kept.
然后你也许就会明白, 为什么会有这些秘密
MAXTIBLE: You see this?
你看见这个了吗？
RUTH: What is it?
这是什么?
MAXTIBLE: A piece of ordinary metal of very little value, would you not say so?
一小块普通的金属, 它不值钱, 你不觉得吗？
RUTH: I suppose so.
我也这么想
MAXTIBLE: What does it weigh? A few pounds? Five, six, shall we say?
它有多重？好几磅？ 5磅, 6磅, 我们估计
MAXTIBLE: For centuries now, men have searched for the greatest secret of all.
几个世纪以来, 人类都在探索这项终极秘密
MAXTIBLE: Some say it was known to the ancient alchemists.
有的人说, 古代的炼金术士知道这个
MAXTIBLE: Some say that the secret never existed at all.
有的人说, 这项秘密从来不存在
MAXTIBLE: But still, the stories and the rumours, and the search goes on!
尽管如此, 故事、流言, 以及探索, 都从未停止
RUTH: What secret?!
什么秘密
MAXTIBLE: The transmutation of metal into gold. Changing metal into gold.
金属到金子的转化方法, 把金属变成金子
MAXTIBLE: Now, perhaps, do you begin to understand a little?
现在, 你是不是开始有点明白了？
MAXTIBLE: To possess such a secret would mean power and influence beyond all imagination.
拥有这样一向秘密就意味着有了不可想象的力量和权利
MAXTIBLE: And I am about to discover this secret. Nothing will stop me. Nothing! Nobody!
而我正要发现这个秘密了。没有什么可以挡住我, 没有谁！
DALEK: Name?
名字?
VICTORIA: Victoria.
维多利亚
DALEK: Louder!
大声点
VICTORIA: Victoria Waterfield!
维多利亚-瓦特菲尔德!
DALEK: Inspection is over. Return to your room.
检视结束了, 回到你的房间去吧
(Victoria goes back to her room and the lights goes out.)
(Jamie gives Kemel one end of the rope, and circles around the Dalek.)
(Together they pull the rope, sending the Dalek crashing into the fireplace.)
JAMIE: Well, that's fixed that one.
(They run to beneath the gallery.)
(Kemel throws the rope over the banister and pulls it tight.)
(Jamie climbs the rope.)
(He reaches the top and climbs onto the landing.)
(Kemel starts climbing up.)
Look out, the rail's going to break!
(He continues climbing.)
(Jamie helps Kemel onto the landing.)
JAMIE: Miss Waterfield? Can you open the door? We've come to get you.
Waterfield 小姐, 你能把门打开吗？我们来救你了
(Unnoticed, a Dalek comes out of the shadows.)